Guide to the Carl H. King Papers, 1918-1973 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carl H. King papers 1918-1973 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
King, Carl Howie, 1898-1967.
14.5 linear feet Extent: Approximately 10,000 Items
Methodist minister from Salisbury (Rowan Co.), N.C., King was executive secretary of the Methodist Board of Education of the Western North Carolina Conference, 1934-1967. His wife, Mary Eskridge King, was active in affairs of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and president of the Women's Society of Christian Service of the Western North Carolina Conference, 1960-1964. The papers of Carl Howie King and of Mary Eskridge King span the dates 1918-1973, and document aspects of Methodism and politics and social movements in North Carolina during the later 20th century. Types of materials chiefly consist of correspondence, meeting and conference files, and biographical material on Carl and Mary King. Mary King's papers form the majority of the collection and document her extensive involvement in the Methodist Church and its organizations; topics of interest include Christian education, political conservatism and the John Birch Society, the Civil Rights movement, prayer in schools, the Vietnam War, student unrest, and communism. Carl King's papers include correspondence, writings, and notes from his student days at Trinity College, now Duke University, and Yale University.
RL.00780
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Provenance
The Carl H. King Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1973.
Collection Overview
The papers of Carl Howie King and of Mary Eskridge King span the dates 1918-1973 and document aspects of Methodism and politics and social movements in North Carolina during the later part of the 20th century. C. H. King was executive secretary of the Methodist Board of Education of the Western North Carolina Conference, 1934-1967. His papers, housed in the Carl King Papers and Writings Series, consist principally of letters from people to whom he had sent copies of his pamphlet, "Historical Highlights of the Educational Ministry." Also present are materials from his student days at Trinity College (now Duke University), Durham, N.C., and Yale. Mary Eskridge King was active in affairs of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and president of the Women’s Society of Christian Service of the Western North Carolina Conference, 1960-1964. Her papers, in the Mary Eskridge King Series which forms the majority of the collection, concern her activities in Methodist affairs on the local, regional, and national level, as president of the Women’s Society of Christian Service, and her service on various other church boards and special committees. Topics of interest in her papers include Methodism and public affairs, including political conservatism and the John Birch Society, the Civil Rights movement, prayer in schools, the Vietnam War, student unrest, and communism.
Subject Headings
Christian education -- United States; Christianity and politics -- Methodist Church; Civil rights movements -- United States; Duke University -- History; King, Carl Howie, 1898-1967; King, Mary Eskridge; Methodist Church -- Clergy -- Correspondence; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- History; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina; Religion and politics -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Salisbury (N.C.); Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- United States; Women and religion -- Methodist Church; Yale University. Divinity School
Contents of Collection
- Carl King Papers and Writings Series, 1918-1968, (4 boxes)
  - Papers, 1918-1968; Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1967, Printed Material (Box 27)
  - Writings, 1924-1929 (Student Notes) (Box 28)
  - Writings, 1929, Miscellaneous (Box 29)
- Mary Eskridge King Series, 1941-1973, (25 boxes) (Box 29)
  - Methodism and Higher Education in North Carolina, 1957-1972 (Box 2)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service: 1954-1965 (Box 2)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service: 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service: 1969-1970 (Box 4)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service: 1971-1972 Oct. (Box 5)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service: 1972 Dec. and n.d. (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Council of Churches, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Methodism, Board of Hospitals, 1963-1974 (Box 6)
  - Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - Methodism and Public Affairs, 1952-1961 (Box 6)
  - Methodism and Public Affairs, 1961-1971 (Box 7)
  - Western North Carolina Conference and the Southeast Jurisdictional Conference, 1963-1969 June (Box 7)
  - Western North Carolina Conference and the Southeast Jurisdictional Conference, 1969-1973 (Box 8)
  - Western North Carolina Conference and the Southeast Jurisdictional Conference, 1963-1972 (Box 9)
  - Ecumenicalism, National Council of Churches, and World Council of Churches, 1952-1967 (Box 9)
  - Ecumenicalism, National Council of Churches, and World Council of Churches, 1952-1967 (Box 10)
  - National and World Councils of Churches, 1969 Nov.-1972 (Box 11)
  - United Methodist Church, Board of Missions: 1962-1964 (Box 11)
  - United Methodist Church, Board of Missions: 1965-1968 Mar. (Box 12)
  - United Methodist Church, Board of Missions: 1968 Apr.-1969 (Box 13)
  - United Methodist Church, Board of Missions: 1970-1971 (Box 14)
  - United Methodist Church, Board of Missions: 1971-1972 and n.d. (Box 15)
  - United Methodist Church: General Conferences: 1960-1964 (Box 16)
  - United Methodist Church: General Conferences: 1964-1972 (Box 17)
  - United Methodist Church: General Conferences: 1972 (Box 18)
  - United Methodist Church: General Conferences: 1972 and n.d. (Box 19)
  - United Methodist Church and Human Rights and Social Concerns: 1957-1966 (Box 19)
  - United Methodist Church and Human Rights and Social Concerns: 1967-1969 (Box 20)
  - United Methodist Church and Human Rights and Social Concerns: 1969-1969 (Box 21)
  - United Methodist Church and Human Rights and Social Concerns: 1969-1970 (Box 22)
  - United Methodist Church and Human Rights and Social Concerns: 1970-1973 (Box 23)
  - United Methodist Church and Human Rights and Social Concerns: Undated (Box 24)
  - United Methodist Church, First Methodist Church, Charlotte, NC, 1968-1972 (Box 24)
  - United Methodist Development Fund, 1972 (Box 25)
  - United Methodist Church, Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 25)
  - United Methodist Church, National Convocation of Methodist Youth, 1959 (Box 25)
  - United Methodist Church, Conference Schools of Christian Missions, 1969-1970 (Box 25)
  - Regional Schools Committee, 1970 Aug. 28-1972 June (Box 25)
  - Biblical Studies, Program Planning, and related (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1965 (Box 25)
  - Biblical Studies, Program Planning, and Miscellaneous, 1965-1973 (Box 26)
  - Obituaries, Bibliography (Box 26)